Guide to the Cominco American Inc., Douglas Mine and Concentrator Records 1957-1976
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
Cominco American, Inc., Douglas Mine and Concentrator Records
1957-1976
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana--Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 614
Cominco American, Inc.
13.0 linear feet
The Douglas Mine and Concentrator operated in Granite County, Montana from 1964-1968 under the ownership of the Montana Phosphate Products Company and later Cominco American, Inc. The records contain material related to the development, operation and dismantling of the mine and concentrator, as well as several maps and engineering drawings illustrating the Douglas Operation and other nearby mines owned by these same companies.
Historical Note
In 1962 the Montana Phosphate Products Company, based in Garrison, Montana, began a significant phosphate mining and milling project in the Maxville Mining District of Granite County, Montana. In addition to the potential profit for the company, it was hoped that the exploitation of area phosphate deposits would boost the region’s economy. The Douglas Mine and Concentrator located nine miles south of Drummond, Montana on Douglas Creek were a major part of this development. Montana Phosphate Products Company began underground mining at this location in 1962. By 1964 the mine employed approximately 110 workers and was steadily producing phosphate rock.
The advent of phosphate mining in Granite County during the early 1960s perked the interest of other significant firms, particularly Cominco American, Inc., the American branch of a large Canadian mining and smelting corporation. Cominco had been mining in adjacent Powell County, Montana for years, sometimes in partnership with Montana Phosphate Products Company, and saw the expanding Douglas Operation as a natural addition to its holdings. In 1965, Cominco American, Inc. gained control of the Douglas Mine and continued to expand operations at that location. The Douglas Concentrator began milling phosphate rock in 1965, and Cominco started one of Montana’s few open pit phosphate mines on their Douglas Creek site in 1967. During these years of steady expansion, production peaked and the operation employed nearly 160 men and women.
Despite promising production and heavy investment by both Montana Phosphate Products Company and Cominco American, Inc., the operation was closed down in 1968. In 1972, Cominco American, Inc. hired the Bechtel Corporation to dismantle the Douglas Concentrator and send all salvageable equipment to Greenland for use in a mine operated by Greenex, a subsidiary of Cominco. Sections of the mine and tailings at the Douglas site have since been reclaimed by the Montana Waste Cleanup Bureau, while other portions remain on the Montana DEQ shortlist, and may require further reclamation.
This collection contains materials related to the development, operation and dismantling of the Douglas Mine and Concentrator, located in Granite County, Montana, by the Montana Phosphate Products Company and Cominco American, Inc. during the 1960s and early 1970s. The records offers insight into mining philosophies and trends of that time, as well as providing information on the day-to-day operations of a phosphate mine and milling operation in Western Montana.
Series I, Mine and Concentrator Development, contains materials related to the development of the Douglas Operation by the Montana Phosphate Products Company, and later Cominco American, Inc., beginning in 1962 and extending into mid-1960s. Included are cost quotations and advertisements for various mining and milling equipment, engineering drawings, construction specifications, cost projections and other materials. This series gives an overview of state-of-the-art phosphate mining technologies in the 1960s, as well as the amount of financial investment and work necessary to undertake such a mining project.
Series II, Mine and Concentrator Operations, contains daily and monthly reports, maintenance schedules, studies, correspondence, financial calculations, and other miscellaneous materials created by the Montana Phosphate Products Company and Cominco Amerincan, Inc. during the operation of the Douglas Mine and Concentrator from 1962-1968. This material provides a look into the day-to-day operations of a phosphate mine and concentrator operating in Western Montana during the 1960s.
Series III, Concentrator Dismantling, contains correspondence and daily reports, as well as other miscellaneous material related to the dismantling of the Douglas Concentrator in 1972. This action was authorized by Cominco American, Inc. and carried out by the Bechtel Corporation. The series is representative of how Cominco American, Inc. was able to salvage much of the equipment at its Douglas Creek location for use in another mining project in Greenland.
Series IV, Maps and Drawings, contains numerous oversized maps and drawings depicting the Douglas Operation and other Montana Phosphate Products Company and Cominco American, Inc. mines in the region, including the Anderson (Warm Springs), Brock, Luke, and Relyea Mines. The materials range in subject from underground mines to dam cross-sections to construction specifications.
Series I: Mine and Concentrator Development, 2.25 linear feet, 1962-1966 and undated
Series II: Mine and Concentrator Operations, 8.0 linear feet, 1957-1968 and undated
Series III: Concentrator Dismantling, 0.5 linear feet, 1972
Series IV: Maps and Drawings, 2.25 linear feet, 1961-1976 and undated
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana--Missoula.
These records were found at the mine site and given to the K. Ross Toole Archives by an unknown donor in the mid-1980s.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Montana Phosphate Products Company
Mining corporations--Montana; Phosphate mines and mining--Montana--Granite County; Business records--Montana
Montana; Mines and Mineral Resources
- Mine and Concentrator Development, 1962-1966; Series I
  - Grinding, Electric Motor, 1962 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Grinding, Flotation Machines, 1962-1965 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Filtering, Thickeners, 1962 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Filtering, Thickeners, EIMCO Corporation, 1962-1966 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Filtering, Albany Felt Company, 1964-1965 (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Filtering, AMETEK Filtration Fabrics, 1963-1964 (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Drying, 1962-1965 (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Drying, Dorrco Fluosolids Drying System, Dorr-Oliver, Inc., 1963 (Box-folder 1/8)
  - Drying, Dryers, Dorr-Oliver Inc., 1962-1965 (Box-folder 1/9)
  - Drying, Dryers, Refractory and Insulation, 1963 and undated (Box-folder 1/10)
  - Drying, Dust Collecting, 1964-1965 (Box-folder 1/11)
  - Loading, General, 1962-1964 (Box-folder 1/12)
  - Loading, Air Slides and Loading Chutes, 1963 (Box-folder 1/13)
  - Loading, Bucket Elevators, 1963 (Box-folder 1/14)
  - Loading, Car Movers, 1963 (Box-folder 1/15)
  - Loading, Car Movers, Northern Pacific Railway, 1962-1963 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Loading, Elevators, Link Belt Company, 1963-1965 (Box-folder 2/2)
  - Loading, Weightometer Conveyors, 1962 (Box-folder 2/3)
  - Loading, Weightometer Conveyors, Fuller Company, 1962-1963 (Box-folder 2/4)
  - Loading, Weightometer Conveyors, Sutorbuilt Corporation, 1963 (Box-folder 2/5)
  - Tailings, Disposal, 1962-1964 (Box-folder 2/6)
  - Tailings, Thickener, EIMCO Corporation, 1963-1964 (Box-folder 2/7)
  - Pumps, General, 1962-1964 (Box-folder 2/8)
  - Pumps, Denver Equipment Company, 1962-1965 (Box-folder 2/9)
  - Pumps, Galigher Company, 1962-1965 (Box-folder 3/1)
  - Piping, 1963-1966 (Box-folder 3/2)
  - Valves and Sumps, 1963-1964 (Box-folder 3/3)
  - Instruments, General, 1962-1963 (Box-folder 3/4)
  - Instruments, Automatic Timing & Controls, Inc., 1963 (Box-folder 3/5)
  - Instruments, Bailey Meter Company, 1963 and undated (Box-folder 3/6)
  - Instruments, Beckman Instruments, Inc., 1963-1964 (Box-folder 3/7)
  - Instruments, Foxboro Company, 1962 (Box-folder 3/8)
  - Instruments, Motor Control Centers, 1962-1963 (Box-folder 3/9)
  - Instruments, Taylor Instrument Companies, 1962-1964 (Box-folder 3/10)
  - Instruments, Temperature Control, 1963-1964 (Box-folder 3/11)
  - Plant Air System, 1963 (Box-folder 3/12)
  - Drives, General, 1962 (Box-folder 4/1)
  - Drives, General, 1962-1963 (Box-folder 4/2)
  - Laboratory Equipment, 1963-1964 (Box-folder 4/3)
  - Laboratory Equipment, 1963-1964 (Box-folder 4/4)
  - Cranes, 1963 (Box-folder 4/5)
  - Cranes, Harnischefeger Corporation, 1962-1963 (Box-folder 4/6)
  - General and Miscellaneous, 1962-1965 (Box-folder 4/7)
  - Concentrator Construction Specifications, undated (Box-folder 4/8)
  - Cost Predictions, undated (Box-folder 4/9)
  - Douglas Creek Tailings Dam Testing, 1964 (Box-folder 4/10)
  - Electronic Controls, 1963 (Box-folder 4/11)
  - Field Notebook entitled "6315 Plant Control & Ties", undated (Box-folder 4/12)
  - Fire Protection, 1962 and undated (Box-folder 4/13)
  - Gas and Burners, 1963 and undated (Box-folder 5/1)
  - Ground and Soil Data, 1963 and undated (Box-folder 5/2)
  - Invoices from Kaiser Engineers, 1964-1965 (Box-folder 5/3)
  - Miscellaneous Equipment Quotations, 1962-1963 (Box-folder 5/4)
  - Painting, 1963 (Box-folder 5/5)
  - Process Equipment to be Purchased by Owner, 1963 (Box-folder 5/6)
  - Water Heaters, Cooley Company, 1963-1964 (Box-folder 5/7)
  - Western Knapp Engineering Company, Monthly Job Cost Report, 1963 (Box-folder 5/8)
  - Western Knapp Engineering Company, Requests for Quotations, 1962-1963 (Box-folder 5/9)
  - List of 815 Original Plant Series Drawings, undated (Box-folder 5/10)
  - Miscellaneous Drawings, 1963-1964 (Box-folder 5/11)
  - Miscellaneous Drawings, 1958-1964 (Box-folder 5/12)
- Mine and Concentrator Operations, 1957-1968; Series II
  - Douglas Mine Underground Daily Reports, 1966 (Box OS1)
  - Douglas Mine Underground Daily Reports, 1967 (Box OS2)
  - Douglas Mine Underground Daily Reports, 1968 (Box OS2)
  - Douglas Mine Drilling and Loading Reports for Locations 5213C-5312, 1966-1967 (Box-folder 5/13)
  - Douglas Mine Drilling and Loading Reports for Locations 5313B-5319B, 1966-1967 (Box-folder 5/14)
  - Douglas Mine Drilling and Loading Reports for Locations 5407-5419C, 1966-1967 (Box-folder 6/1)
  - Douglas Mine Drilling and Loading Reports for Locations 5505C-5517C, 1966-1968 (Box-folder 6/2)
  - Douglas Mine Drilling and Loading Reports for Locations 5519B-5813, 1966-1968 (Box-folder 6/3)
  - Douglas Mine Production Reports, 1964-1965 (Box-folder 6/4)
  - Douglas Mine Daily Underground Time Sheets, 1967 (Box-folder 6/5)
  - Douglas Mine Daily Underground Time Sheets, 1967 (Box-folder 6/6)
  - Douglas Mine Daily Underground Time Sheets, 1967 (Box-folder 6/7)
  - Douglas Concentrator Daily Assay Reports, 1964 (Box-folder 6/8)
  - Douglas Concentrator Daily Assay Reports, 1964 (Box-folder 6/9)
  - Douglas Concentrator Daily Assay Reports, 1965 (Box-folder 6/10)
  - Douglas Concentrator Daily Assay Reports, 1965 (Box-folder 7/1)
  - Douglas Concentrator Daily Assay Reports, 1965 (Box-folder 7/2)
  - Douglas Concentrator Daily Assay Reports, 1965 (Box-folder 7/3)
  - Douglas Concentrator Daily Assay Reports, 1965 (Box-folder 7/4)
  - Douglas Concentrator Daily Assay Reports, 1965 (Box-folder 7/5)
  - Douglas Concentrator Daily Assay Reports, 1965 (Box-folder 7/6)
  - Douglas Concentrator Daily Assay Reports, 1965 (Box-folder 7/7)
  - Douglas Concentrator Daily Assay Reports, 1966 (Box-folder 7/8)
  - Douglas Concentrator Daily Assay Reports, 1966 (Box-folder 7/9)
  - Douglas Concentrator Daily Assay Reports, 1966 (Box-folder 7/10)
  - Douglas Concentrator Daily Assay Reports, 1966 (Box-folder 7/11)
  - Daily Concentrator Reports, 1964 (Box-folder 8/1)
  - Daily Concentrator Reports, 1964 (Box-folder 8/2)
  - Daily Concentrator Reports, 1965 (Box-folder 8/3)
  - Daily Concentrator Reports, 1965 (Box-folder 8/4)
  - Daily Concentrator Reports, 1965 (Box-folder 8/5)
  - Daily Concentrator Reports, 1965 (Box-folder 8/6)
  - Concentrator Daily Plant Service Reports, 1966 (Box-folder 8/7)
  - Concentrator Daily Plant Service Reports, 1966 (Box-folder 8/8)
  - Concentrator Daily Plant Service Reports, 1966 (Box-folder 8/9)
  - Concentrator Daily Plant Service Reports, 1966 (Box-folder 8/10)
  - Concentrator Monthly Reports, 1964-1966 (Box-folder 8/11)
  - Douglas Operation Feeder and Crusher Daily Reports, 1966 (Box-folder 9/1)
  - Douglas Operation Feeder and Crusher Daily Reports, 1966 (Box-folder 9/2)
  - Douglas Operation Feeder and Crusher Daily Reports, 1966 (Box-folder 9/3)
  - Douglas Operation Feeder and Crusher Daily Reports, 1966 (Box-folder 9/4)
  - Filter Bag Reports, 1965-1966 (Box-folder 9/5)
  - Concentrator Daily Grinding and Flotation Report, undated (Box-folder 9/6)
  - Reports on Wet Tons Delivered to Coarse Ore Bin, 1964-1967 (Box-folder 9/7)
  - Ore Storage Silo Inventories, 1968 (Box-folder 9/8)
  - Monthly Maintenance Reports, 1967-1968 and undated (Box-folder 9/9)
  - Equipment Maintenance Schedule Cards, undated (Box-folder 9/10)
  - Equipment Maintenance Schedule Cards, undated (Box-folder 9/11)
  - Equipment Maintenance Schedule Cards, undated (Box-folder 9/12)
  - Douglas Concentrator Maintenance Backlog, 1965 and undated (Box-folder 10/1)
  - High Voltage Breaker Maintenance Check-off Sheet, 1966 (Box-folder 10/2)
  - Maintenance Department, Miscellaneous Material, 1967-1968 and undated (Box-folder 10/3)
  - Miscellaneous Maintenance Manuals, undated (Box-folder 10/4)
  - Concentrator Cost Calculations, 1965 and undated (Box-folder 10/5)
  - Cost and Variance Statements, 1965 (Box-folder 10/6)
  - Economic Design and Calculations, 1965 and undated (Box-folder 10/7)
  - Mine Operation Cost Calculations, 1965 (Box-folder 10/8)
  - Specific Gravity Samples of Douglas Ore, 1965 (Box-folder 10/9)
  - Metallurgy Studies, 1965-1966 (Box-folder 10/10)
  - Atomic Absorption Analysis, 1966 (Box-folder 10/11)
  - Fatty Acid Saponification, 1966 (Box-folder 10/12)
  - Plant Water Supply Studies, 1966 (Box-folder 10/13)
  - Sink-Float and Floatation Testing on Phosphate Rock, 1966 (Box-folder 10/14)
  - Emergency Tailings Thickeners, 1967 (Box-folder 10/15)
  - System for Testing the Moisture and Content of Phosphate Rock, 1967 (Box-folder 10/16)
  - Concentrator Operation Manuals and Instructions, undated (Box-folder 10/17)
  - Forms to Accompany Concrete Cylinders, Montana State Highway Department, 1966 (Box-folder 10/18)
  - Labor and Related Expenses, 1966-1968 and undated (Box-folder 10/19)
  - Mine and Mill Code Sheets, undated (Box-folder 10/20)
  - Painting Agreement, 1968 (Box-folder 10/21)
  - Purchasing and Warehousing, 1967-1968 (Box-folder 10/22)
  - Quotations and Information on Compressed Air Drying and Cleaning Equipment, 1968 (Box-folder 10/23)
  - Various Publications, 1966 (Box-folder 10/24)
  - Water and Power Information, 1957-1967 and undated (Box-folder 11/1)
  - Weekly Contract Summary, 1963-1965 (Box-folder 11/2)
  - Work Order 225, Revision of Mine Bunker at Douglas Mine, 1968 (Box-folder 11/3)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1964-1968 (Box-folder 11/4)
  - Miscellaneous Meeting Minutes and Reports, 1966 and undated (Box-folder 11/5)
- Concentrator Dismantling, 1972; Series III
  - Incoming to Construction from other Departments, 1972 (Box-folder 11/6)
  - Outgoing from Field to Engineering, 1972 (Box-folder 11/7)
  - Incoming from Engineering, 1972 (Box-folder 11/8)
  - Incoming Engineering from other Departments, 1972 (Box-folder 11/9)
  - Incoming from Purchasing to Field, 1972 (Box-folder 11/10)
  - Requisition Register, 1972 (Box-folder 11/11)
  - Incoming from Purchasing to other Departments, 1972 (Box-folder 11/12)
  - Outgoing to Estimating from Field, 1972 (Box-folder 11/13)
  - Code of Accounts, 1972 (Box-folder 11/14)
  - Incoming from Planning and Scheduling to Field, 1972 (Box-folder 11/15)
  - Detailed Engineering and Construction Schedule, 1972 (Box-folder 11/16)
  - Incoming from Labor Relations to Field, 1972 (Box-folder 11/17)
  - Outgoing to Labor Relations from Field, 1972 (Box-folder 11/18)
  - Outgoing from Equipment Department, 1972 (Box-folder 11/19)
  - Outgoing from Engineering to Client, 1972 (Box-folder 11/20)
  - Conference Notes between Home Office and Client, 1972 (Box-folder 11/21)
  - Monthly Construction Progress Report, 1972 (Box-folder 11/22)
  - Critical Crafts Report, 1972 (Box-folder 11/23)
  - Weekly Construction Activities, 1972 (Box-folder 11/24)
  - Force Report, 1972 (Box-folder 11/25)
  - Labor and Safety Report, 1972 (Box-folder 11/26)
  - Historical Report for Job 10090, 1972 (Box-folder 11/27)
  - Tools, 1972 (Box-folder 11/28)
  - Equipment, Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1972 (Box-folder 11/29)
  - Incoming from Vendors to Field, 1972 (Box-folder 11/30)
  - Outgoing to Vendors from Field, 1972 (Box-folder 11/31)
  - Daily Reading File, 1972 (Box-folder 11/32)
- Maps and Drawings, 1961-1976 and undated; Series IV
  - Douglas Mine, Ore Extraction Cross-sections, 1966 (Item 1)
  - Douglas Mine, Proposed "A" Cross-section and Road, 1 Sheet, 1968 (Item 2)
  - Douglas Mine, Proposed B-North Development, 4 Sheets, undated (Item 3)
  - Douglas Mine, Chute Cutouts for 5201C, 2 Sheets, undated (Item 4)
  - Douglas Mine, Proposed C-South Development, 2 Sheets, undated (Item 5)
  - Douglas Mine Phosphate Ore Reserves, 1 Sheet, undated (Item 6)
  - Douglas Mine, Additions and Raises, 9 Sheets, 1963-1968 (Item 7)
  - Douglas Mine, D-Bed Strip Mining Cross-sections, 19 Sheets, undated (Item 8)
  - Douglas Mine, D Stockpile Open Pit Mining Cross-sections, 4 Sheets, undated (Item 9)
  - Douglas Mine, Canal Base Line Survey, 1 Sheet, undated (Item 10)
  - Douglas Mine, Drift and Tunnel Locations and Elevations, 9 Sheets, Undated (Item 11)
  - Douglas Mill Drawings and Specifications, 4 Sheets, 1966 (Item 12)
  - Douglas Mill Construction Drawings, 1962-1963 (Item 13)
  - Douglas Mill Construction Drawings, 1962-1963 (Item 14)
  - Douglas Mill Construction Drawings, 1963 (Item 15)
  - Douglas Mill Boiler-Steam Complex Construction Drawings, 1963 (Item 16)
  - Douglas Mine, Tailings Capacity, 2 Sheets, 1963 (Item 17)
  - Douglas Mine, Tailings Plans, 11 Sheets, 1963-1964 (Item 18)
  - Douglas Operation, Cross-sections of Tailing Pond, 1 Sheet, 1966 (Item 19)
  - Douglas Creek Tailings and Diversion Dam, 1963 (Item 20)
  - Douglas Operation Tailings Pond, 4 Sheets, 1961-1963 and undated (Item 21)
  - Douglas Mine, Tailings Pond, 21 Sheets, 1963-1964 and undated (Item 22)
  - Douglas Mine, Tailings "Pond B" Cross-sections, 2 Sheets, undated (Item 23)
  - Douglas Mine, Tailings Pond, undated (Item 24)
  - Douglas Mine, Tailings Pond, 4 drawings, 1963 and undated (Item 25)
  - Cross-section Douglas Tailings Dam, Stage 1, Rocky Mountain Construction, 1 Sheet, 1963 (Item 26)
  - Cross-section Douglas Tailings Dam, Stage 1, Rocky Mountain Construction, 1 Sheet, 1964 (Item 27)
  - Douglas Creek Dam Cross-sections, 2 Sheets, undated (Item 28)
  - Douglas Creek Dam Cross-sections, 1 Sheet, undated (Item 29)
  - Douglas Mine, Miscellaneous Dam Cross-sections, 3 Sheets, undated (Item 30)
  - Douglas Mine, Main Dam Drawings, 4 Sheets, undated (Item 31)
  - Water Supply Storage Dam, 3 Sheets, 1963 (Item 32)
  - Douglas Mine, Proposed Access Roads and Elevations, 4 Sheets, 1967 (Item 33)
  - Northern Pacific Railway, Prod Tracking to serve Douglas Mine, 1 Sheet, 1962 (Item 34)
  - Douglas Mill, Cross-section of Proposed Railway Grade, 1 Sheet, 1963 (Item 35)
  - Douglas Operation, Miscellaneous Cross-sections, 18 Sheets, undated (Item 36)
  - Tonnage/Cost Budgetary Chart, 1 Sheet, 1966-1967 (Item 37)
  - Willow Creek Storage Dam, USDA, undated (Item 38)
  - Willow Creek Storage Dam, USDA Soil Conservation, 1 Sheets, undated (Item 39)
  - Anderson, Brock and Relyea Mines, 1 Sheet, 1961 (Item 40)
  - Brock Mine, 4 Sheets, 1966-1975 (Item 41)
  - Dunkelberg Mine, Sheet, 1965 (Item 42)
  - South Luke Mine, 1 Sheet, 1976 (Item 43)
  - Warm Springs (Anderson) Mine, Sheet, 1973 (Item 44)
  - South Warm Springs (Anderson) Mine, 2 Sheets, 1975 (Item 45)